Leah: Being a backend developer
can be very fulfilling and
they're constantly updating their
knowledge and learning new skills.
It can also be rewarding
financially as it pays well.
The role involves a lot of problem
solving and suits someone who is
methodical and enjoys logical challenges.
Work however can often overrun
the usual working hours as when
problems arise they must be dealt
with and may not get resolved
before the end of the working day.
Let's hear from a backend developer to
learn more about what the role involves...
Tom: I'm Tom, I'm currently working
as a contract backend developer.
In terms of qualifications, I've got a
bachelor's degree in computer programming.
Before I started contracting as a
backend developer, I spent three years
working as a junior web developer.
Some people study for a master's
degree and go straight into backend
development, but if you've got the
programming experience, you can do
it even without a degree if you can
show that you've got the experience.
I've been working as a backend
developer for about three years.
Initially started working for a web design
company as a junior web developer where
I was working on developing frontend
platforms using languages like HTML5 and
JavaScript, and they were really useful
for learning about integration before
I transitioned to backend development.
I also learned quite a lot of different
programming techniques, which were
useful for backend development,
like writing APIs and SQL databases.
And I really enjoyed that aspect of it.
I do enjoy being a backend developer.
So I really enjoy writing code and sort
of setting up servers, providing services
for user interfaces and things like that.
And if you're creative and you enjoy
continually developing new skills,
then it's a really good job to do
because it's really satisfying at
the end of it to be able to see
what you put time into then working.
It's also interesting to see how projects
develop over time with continuous
integration and development practices.
Responsibilities vary
depending on what the job is.
But it's often developing and
maintaining code that drives applications
from behind the user interface.
So that's where it's really useful
to know something about frontend
development, because with backend
development, you're essentially
translating  the user input on the
frontend side and into the desired result
or correctly storing data behind it.
So in general, some of the
responsibilities include adhering
to GDPR rules and principles when
you're using/storing data and
making sure that that's secure.
Implementing security measures and
keeping the data you've collected
safe, again, similar to GDPR.
And creating and writing code
libraries for the scaling of the
web application and debugging these.
It's also really important to be on
top of the technology that's being
implemented in your applications to
make sure that it's the most up to date.
You have to communicate
well with the client.
Keep on top of sprint meetings and just
generally keep the client happy, really.
Because I work as a contractor,
quite often I'm working remote so
hours can vary a bit, but you do
have to be responsive to emails and
normal working times and you know,
attending meetings when it's necessary.
So for example, typically the day might
start with a short meeting with the
client or with colleagues that you're
working with to sort of discuss recent
issues and how they'll be resolved and
then move on to work on whatever's the
highest priority that you have to do.
So that might be urgent bug fixes or
fixing new issues that have arisen.
Typically using languages like
Java, Python, PHP, Ruby, or C#.
And just ensuring that you're
keeping the application optimised in
terms of scaling and speed really.
Yeah, since I'm working [in] contracting,
often the timescales are quite short,
so you occasionally have to put in
extra hours, but generally it's quite
satisfying to see the end result.
Keeping on top of the meetings with, like,
collaboration tools, like GitHub for code
or Slack for agile and attending meetings.
It's a good role for somebody who's
sort of interested code and sort
of application and structures.
And it can be quite challenging, but at
the same time, you sort of have to be
quite innovative for it to solve some
of the problems, which can be quite
challenging, but also quite interesting.
So I think that it's good if you've,
if you've got that sort of you
know, creative pursuit, basically.